Jeffrey Lang

Louisville, Colorado, United States



jefflang@govcompli.com



linkedin.com/in/jeffrey-lang

Summary

I make a living transforming contractor systems to provide better operational insight, reduce manual processes, and improve compliance and audit. I do this by combining a deep understanding of government compliance requirements, system and database structures, and application development across all aspects of business operations.

I learned early on in my days as a DCAA auditor that government contracting can be a blessing and a curse. It can be a great source of external funding to provide necessary resources for early stage development and lowrisk delivery. However, the compliance and reporting requirements are burdensome and confusing. Since 2012, I have been helping government contractors overcome these burdens and streamline operations to capitalize on this amazing source of funding.

After my years at DCAA, I worked my way up from a small consultancy, to becoming Director of Finance Systems and Audit at a \$60m+ R&D lab, to now owning my own consultancy and providing a wide-range of services to clients with funding ranging from small grants to \$10's of millions of dollars in FFP deliverable contracts.

I have continued to develop my skills throughout this journey and have been able to:

- -take contractors from failing to passing systems audit's in less than 6 months.
- -implemented a wide variety of systems from Deltek to Quickbooks to Aspire, and developed processes around those systems to make them government compliant and efficient, showing reductions in manual processes and errors.
- -negotiated agreements, managed dozens of projects, and completed all manner of reporting requirements across a dozen government funding programs.
- -integrate systems data to allow for cross-platform reporting and increased operational insights. I earned a Master's in Computer Information Systems after years of struggling to understand backend architectures and data transformation.
- -design and document processes and policies that give employees the guidance and confidence they need to perform their jobs.
- -develop tools and systems that serve the needs of the organization from individual contributors to CEO's especially when it comes to budgets, revenue forecasting, and project performance.

My passion has always been empowering people to do higher-level work. This is evident in the work I do for organizations, as well as my hobbies of teaching yoga, meditation, fitness and diet. I hope you've learned a bit about me and consider working with me in the future. Thanks.

Experience



Founder and Managing Director

GovCompli, Ltd.

Jul 2019 - Present (1 year 5 months +)

Perform system reviews and provide improvement plans for accounting, finance, billing, materials management, project management, and reporting, with an eye on government compliance and industry best practice. Servicing clients with SBIR grants to \$10's of millions of dollars in FFP deliverable manufacturing contracts.

Develop custom applications and business solutions when COTS do not provide for specific needs and requirements. Getting stakeholder feedback to tailor solutions for maximum value and efficiency. # Educate and advise C-suite executives on business planning, budget monitoring, resource forecasting and allocation, internal audit, and systems architecture.

Lead implementation of government compliant systems, from selection, to go-live, providing implementation plans, managing outside vendors, developing systems integrations, and documenting processes and requirements.

Provide ongoing services for rate computation, monitoring, and approval, proposal and estimation development, revenue recognition, and project management and reporting.

Train staff and analyze operational gap analysis for government compliance activities. Craft policies and procedures to clearly define roles and responsibilities within the organization.



Director of Finance Systems and Audit

PARC, a Xerox Company

2017 - Jul 2019 (2 years 7 months)

Drive and implement the finance systems and process strategy, in addition to oversee all financial reporting, audits, and project invoicing, for this technology research and development firm which serves government and commercial clients with over \$60 million in revenue

Architected, planned and managed the complete overhaul of the forecasting, resource and expense planning systems, transforming the workflow from manual, independent inputs in Excel, to automated, scripted updates within a SQL database, within 5 months

Engineered cost savings of \$100,000 over four years leading migration of accounting system cloud providers with a team of five outside consultants, internal Sr. Developer, six accounting staff, and CFO through requirements analysis, negotiation, testing, platform integration tool development, user account establishment, and training and deployment in under 6 months

Dotted line management of Sr. & Jr. Operations Analysts, coordinating purchasing, forecasting, project management, budgeting systems development, reporting, and integration

Modelled data reports and analytics using Power BI, Microsoft Excel, and IBM Cognos performing data transformation, joins, and views to satisfy needs of business owners and requirements of customers

Evolved business transparency using database queries and data lake architecture leading crossfunctional teams with Senior Developer to customize financial system workflows and outputs, achieving user satisfaction and efficiency gains across business teams

Responsible for monthly revenue recognition across milestone, installment, cost-type, and ETC type designations resulting in reducing preparation time down from 1.5 to .5 days per month, and three employees to one

Reduced forecasting variance from 10% to less than 5% percent through project planning tool development, and pipeline workflow structure in response to Executive team mandate for improved accuracy



parc Business Operations Manager

PARC, a Xerox Company

2015 - 2017 (3 years)

Led a cross-organizational team for government and commercial operations, designing and deploying a solution across multiple software platforms to aggregate project actual and forecast data, providing a bottoms-up build of revenue forecasts and Monte Carlo Analysis confidence risk intervals

Collaborated with CEO, Senior Executives, Business Development, and Senior Research Scientists, to gather requirements, define scope and then build an excel based costing application to build labor, non-labor, travel and other direct costs, and apply SAG burdens during the pricing phases of commercial and government projects, which reduced preparation time and eliminated costing errors

Implemented a change management model to ensure that any changes made to the forecast were captured and reconciled, reducing time to prepare monthly financial updates by 75%

Removed the need to hire external IT consultants for critical SQL and database support by obtaining Masters in Computer Information Systems

Negotiated over \$50 million in government contracts reviewing IP terms, budget, payment, and revenue recognition filling vacancy for five months as Sr. Contracts Manager, while performing all other duties



parc Financial Analyst Manager

PARC, a Xerox Company

2013 - 2015 (3 years)

Managed staff of three Financial Analysts, oversaw and assisted on over \$100m of proposal pricing, performed all invoicing and financial reporting

Led first successful outcome of DCAA Accounting System audit in over 4 years through process redesign and documentation, drafting policy and procedures across multiple departments, and handling of auditor engagement

Compiled and executed on corrective actions from audit, namely labor and time keeping violations, and development of policies and procedures.

Participated in a 5-month migration of accounting and finance systems to a cloud-based solution, which included evaluating providers, coordinating testing plans, and acting as point person for technical discussions

Sr. Government Compliance Consultant

Kiwi Consulting

2011 - 2012 (2 years)

- Consulted with over 20 clients, ranging from small businesses to multi-national firms, providing expertise and solutions on cost allocations, government compliant systems, audit defense, corrective action planning, and systems design
- Designed QuickBooks based Excel integration that allowed small businesses to develop a government compliant accounting system in less than a day, which was replicated to multiple clients across various industries and government sponsors
- Hired by PARC because of successful consulting partnership

Certified Yoga Instructor

Tune Up Fitness Worldwide, Inc.

2008 - 2011 (4 years)

 Led classes and workshops across the United States, partnering with top-level instructors to lead groups of up to 300 people in movement and education



Senior Auditor

Defense Contract Audit Agency

2005 - 2008 (4 years)

 Performed a variety of compliance, pricing, and operational audits independently, completing working papers, briefing program managers and contracting officers on findings and recommended actions

Education



University of Denver

Full Stack Web Development Certification, Computer Programming 2020 - 2021

Full stack web application building, including HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery, Node.js, PHP, Laravel, Express.js, React.js, Database Theory, MongoDB, MySQL, Command Line, Git.



📕 Boston University - Metropolitan College

Master of Computer Applications (MCA), Computer Information Systems Database Design and Business Intelligence 2015 - 2016

University of Rhode Island - College of Business

Bachelor of Science, Accounting 2000 - 2004



Northfield Mount Hermon School

High School Diploma, Various 1997 - 1999

Skills

Auditing • Accounting • Financial Reporting • Training • Balance • General Ledger • Financial Analysis • Microsoft Excel • DCAA • Strategic Financial Planning